If you've been looking at purchasing a
home in the central Texas area and
you're wondering why your monthly
payments are a little bit higher than
you expected, [music] it may not be the
price of the home, but actually the
property taxes. While the state of Texas
[music] does not have a state income
tax, it does make up for it in other
ways, like [music] property taxes. And
this can be a really big surprise,
especially if you are relocating from
another state or area.
>> Absolutely. Today we'll [music] break
down property taxes in the central Texas
area. We'll cover how to calculate them,
how to budget for them, and what to
[music] expect, and your monthly
payment.
>> Hi, I'm Andrea Dudek, local real estate
broker and expert [music] here with
Jacob Stutard, lending expert in the
area. And today we'll be covering really
everything that you need to know [music]
when it comes to property taxes.
>> Let's do it.
[music]
So, why do property taxes matter?
Property taxes matter because they're
going to be a major part of your total
mortgage payment.
>> And since the state of Texas does not
have a state income tax, they rely on
other things like property taxes to fund
things like schools, roads, police,
[music] fire, libraries, etc.
>> So, how are property taxes calculated?
Property taxes are calculated by taking
the county's assessed value and
multiplying it by your tax [music] rate.
That's going to be the annual tax bill
on that specific property.
>> And I'll give you an example of where to
find that estimated assessed value here
shortly. But [music] each area, each
county, each city, they're going to vary
in their tax [music] rate. So you might
have some areas, Temple, Belton, Troy,
Celo, inside of city limits, outside
[music] of city limits, all these
different things. I'm not really sure if
there's a method to the madness, but
they'll range from just under 2%
property taxes to even close to 3%. And
that can really and drastically affect
your monthly [music] payment.
>> That's right. So, for example, if you
have a $400,000 house in a specific
area, that tax bill might be around
$7,200 a year.
And if you have that same priced home at
$400,000 in a different area, maybe may
even be in the same city, that tax bill
can be well over $9,000. So, it really
just depends on the taxing area that
that home is located,
>> which again can really really affect
your overall [music] monthly payment.
And while you can gather a lot of this
information to give you an idea, really
the best thing you can do is [music] to
reach out to me and we can figure out
which home you are most interested in or
maybe a couple homes in a couple of
different areas. Jacob can give us
scenarios. We've had plenty of times
where I've [music] sent him an email
said, "Hey, these are the homes that my
client is interested in. This is their
[music] estimated purchase price when
they're looking to close." And he shoots
back, "Here's their estimated closing
costs. cash to close and estimated
monthly payments on a side by side so
the client really get the full picture
on what they're purchasing.
>> Exactly. We try to be as transparent as
possible and it's [music] it's much
easier to give the proper expectations
when there is a specific house you're
looking for. That way we can tailor your
pricing, [music] all the estimates
needed for that specific property to
make sure it fits your budget.
>> Okay, Jacob. So, what's included in
someone's [music] total monthly mortgage
payment? Yeah. So, your total mortgage
payment is going to include your
principal, your interest, your property
taxes, your homeowner's insurance, and
if you have it, also your mortgage
insurance.
>> So, someone's property [music] taxes,
how are those paid each year?
>> Yeah. So, there's going to be set up
what's called an escrow account. So, the
lender is going to set up an escro
account on your behalf. your property
taxes and your homeowners insurance are
going to be placed in that escrow
account. Every year on or the date on
which those property taxes and
homeowners insurance is due, your escro
account will pay those on your behalf.
>> Okay, so something I've seen come up a
lot and I've actually been seeing it
recently on Tik Tok and Instagram is
lenders not escrowing enough [music] in
new construction. Um and so you know
initially we know that if you buy a
brand new home um initially [music] the
county is only assessing on essentially
a vacant lot. They're only assessing on
raw land [music] and then next year the
following year they readjust to now tax
on
>> that's right. Yeah. So when conro new
construction can get kind of funny. In
the beginning, the lenders will do their
best job as as best as we can with the
local taxing areas to to estimate what
your tax rate is going to be the
following year once your county assesses
or reassesses [music] the value of your
home now that the home is built. In some
cases, we can in in the beginning, we
can do the have the escro account set up
based on just a lot. [music] Now, we
will only do that if you have the
understanding that the next year your
property taxes are going to adjust based
on the county's reassessment of the
home's value.
>> But that's definitely going to be a
conversation that's had or should be had
and [music] something you want to look
out for if you are purchasing a new
construction home. I know me as your
realtor, I'm looking at that for you. Of
course, I'm not a lender, but there are
things that I know to look out for, and
I [music] want to make sure that your
monthly payment is going to include like
if I see that the property taxes and
what's being escrowed are incredibly
low. I know our property taxes are high
here. I'm going to say if you're not
using Jacob or someone that I know
that's local, and reputable, did they
have the conversation with you [music]
about when this is reassessed and
they're now assessing on a full property
versus just the land? [music] Because
one of the worst things you want is to
go from a I don't know $2,000 mortgage
payment to a $25 or $2,600 [music]
mortgage payment. You don't those are
not fun surprises.
>> Yeah. Not fun at all. And we try our
best to mitigate that and and uh
communicate [music] that to all of our
clients in the beginning so the
expectations are set.
>> Home exemptions and other discounts. And
so Texas, we do have those property
taxes that are a little bit higher, but
there are exemptions that you can file
[music] for to reduce your property
taxes. Um, those include a homestead
exemption,
over 65 [music] exemption, and exemption
for VA disability.
>> That's right. So, if you're a veteran,
you have a service connected disability,
there are exemptions through the state
of Texas in [music] place to alleviate
your public taxes.
>> Okay. And we're going to actually head
on over to Bellcad to a which is our
local appraisal district. So I can go
ahead and show you where you can find
some really helpful information on how
those actual [music] exemptions work cuz
they all work a little bit different as
well as how you can apply for them.
Okay, as promised, I'm going to go ahead
and show you the appraisal district for
this area. So this is going to cover
most of the Temple, Belton, [music]
Colleen, Celo, Troy, surrounding areas.
You pop a little bit into Corel, Milm,
Williamson, Travis as you get further
[music] out, you can always call me or
do um you know, look up the different
appraisal districts, but this is going
to be the main one [music] for the areas
that I serve here in central Texas. So
you can go to billcad.org.
really great information here. [music]
Two things we're going to cover are
doing a property search so that you can
see taxes and then you can also look up
information on
exemptions. Let's start with property
search 1210 Burger. You just put in the
address here.
And if it's public information, which
most of the time it is, unless it's a
protected individual, a police officer,
um, things of that nature, they can
request to have this information be
private. But generally, you can see an
address. Search by an address or
property ID. Click on it. And [music]
here you have your property address,
market value, appraised. you have your
assessed value. So, what you want to be
paying attention to here is the assessed
value. You can come on down here to
[music] estimated taxes due and you can
see the tax rate currently
on this [music] property
2024 tax rate and what those taxes were.
[music] this home, you can come up to to
exemptions and you'll see the homestead
exemption [music] is the exemption that
they currently have on this property,
which that reduces the taxable amount on
their [music] home.
So, that's how you do your search there.
And then if you head on over to the
homepage, property owner information,
exemption information.
This is where you will find so much
helpful information in terms of the
different exemptions you can file for
based off of your scenario [music] and
any details you might need. And then of
course in the forms here are the places
that you can file them. So, it starts
off with a homestead exemption,
how to qualify, when to file, and when
you can file.
Can also come down more and you have
your over 65 exemption and [music] the
disabled veteran or survivors of a
disabled veteran.
So, really great resource. Check [music]
it out. Hope it's helpful.
We're going to end this with some tips
for buyers. Number one, check the
current tax rate. You can do this
yourself by heading on over to Belcad,
but more easily you can reach out to
Jacob or myself to probably Jacob or and
you guys can run a certain scenario, get
the most accurate information in terms
of assessed value, taxes, and what that
overall scenario in terms of your
monthly mortgage is [music] going to
look like tailored to you. Another tip
that we have for you is please do not
rely on the online websites. I won't
name any names, but there are online
websites out there that don't have or
don't always have the most up-to-date um
property tax information and other
payment information. And nothing is
worse than having to walk all that back
and set the proper expectations based on
the real numbers of the specific house
you're looking at. The biggest tip is
going to be speak with a local expert
that knows the market, that knows where
to find the information, who to connect
you to, so that you're not surprised.
And quite honestly, leave it to the
pros. This isn't your job. It's our job
to make things easier for you, to make
the process seamless, and to give you
the most accurate information.
>> That's right. We're here to serve you.
We're here to make things as smooth and
as easy as possible for you and keep
things as transparent as possible so
that the home buying process is is super
simple and super painless.
>> Mhm. So, if you have any more questions
on property taxes, buying in the central
Texas area, financing, lending, anything
uh real estate related, you can reach
out to Jacob or myself. You can find all
our contact information in the details
below. And if you found this information
helpful, don't forget to like,
subscribe, and click the bell
notification so that you can stay
uptodate on all things real estate here
in Central Texas. Till [music] next
time.
>> Perfect.